Guide to the Oral History of the American Left: Radical Histories Collection OH 002
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Oral History of the American Left: Radical Histories
1920-1980
OH 002
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
20.0 Linear feet
The Tamiment Library at New York University established the Oral History of the American Left in 1976 in order to collect and preserve the memories of veteran activists. These interviews describe seven decades of Left politics from the 1910s through the 1970s. They document the full spectrum of left politics in the twentieth century: Socialism, Communism, Anarchism, Trotskyism, and the New Left. There are interviews with both leaders and rank-and-file activists.
Tamiment Library.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
New York University’s Tamiment Library established the Oral History of the American Left (OHAL) in 1976. The purpose of this project was to expand the archive of American labor and radicalism through the creation of “living documents,” the memories of veteran activists. The idea was “to create an archive of recorded reminiscences by participants in trade union struggles, political organizations, and grass-roots political and cultural activity.” Paul Buhle was the Director of the project. Roger Keeran was Co-Director in the early years. Jon Bloom joined the project in 1977 and worked as an interviewer, coordinator, and fundraiser.
The project began with several years of varied interviewing supported by small grants from the Rabinowitz and Bronson Cutting Foundations. The New Jersey Historical Commission provided funding in 1978 to support a series of interviews on radicalism in New Jersey, during the 1930-1960 period. Later, Ruth F. Prago developed the idea for a radio series based on interviews to be conducted for the OHAL collection, and together with Pacifica Radio the project received a one-year grant from the New York State Council for the Humanities to conduct interviews with twenty-five women about radicalism during the1930s. OHAL received major funding in 1982-1983 from the National Endowment for the Humanities. With this support, Paul Buhle conducted a sweeping oral history of ethnic-immigrant radicalism, its press and fraternal organizations. The NEH grant also enabled OHAL to collect hundreds of hours of interviews made by filmmakers on American anarchism, the Hollywood blacklist, the Communist Party, the Columbia University student strike of 1968, and other subjects.
The project also produced seven issues of a newsletter, and the transcript of a two-day conference co-sponsored by OHAL and the Tamiment Library on the occasion of the opening of the Max Shactman Papers.
Scope and Content Note
The tapes and transcript in the Oral History of the American Left collection came from a variety of sources. Most of the interviews were done by Jon Bloom, Paul Buhle, Bea Lemisch, and Ruth Prago. They cover many subjects including: immigrant/ethnic radicalism, labor, women's history, radical newspapers, fraternal organizations, and student radicalism from 1910s through 1970s. The earliest interviews were done with those men and women who could recall the 1910s -1920s. The effect of the Russian Revolution on the Left in the United States, the formation of social and cultural institutions by the "New Immigrant" groups of all Left political shadings, the history of Socialism and Anarchism, and the troubled early years of American Communism. A particular effort was made to interview rank-and-file or middle-level leadership activists. These women and men for the most part did not leave written records behind so their oral histories are the only historical record that is available. A number of these interviews focused on "radical women." Many interviews focus on the labor movement, particularly the needle trades unions and the early years of the Congress of Industrial Organizations.
The immigrant-ethnic interviews might be the most unique element of the collection. OHAL interviewed representative figures from the Jewish, Finnish, Slovenia, Greek, Hungarian, Polish, Italian, Ukrainian, Lithuanian, Japanese, Scandinavian, and Spanish Left. A handful of tapes recall the African American experience.
Several interviews are with participants in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, who fought in the Spanish Civil War, as the U.S. component of the International Brigades, and several other interviews document related activities. Several interviews document the long tenure of Jasper McLevy, Socialist Party mayor of Bridgeport, Connecticut, 1933-1957.
Ninety-five percent of these interviews are on cassette tapes with accompanying indexes. The rest are transcripts without tapes. Information about format is noted in the inventory.
Notable interviewees include: Notable individuals interviewed include: Herbert Aptheker, Rosalyn Fraad Baxandall, Daniel Berrigan, Abner Berry, James Boggs, George Breitman, Rose Chernin, Malcolm Cowley, Samuel Darcy, Solon De Leon, Hal Draper, Raya Dunayevskaya, Melech Epstein, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Hugo Gellert, Todd Gitlin, Martine Glaberman, Albert Glotzer, Itshe Goldberg, Louis Harap, Michael Harrington, Howard "Stretch" Johnson, Mary Kolehmainen, Meridel Le Sueur, A.B. Magil, Thomas McGrath, Ernest Rice McKinney, Clarence Norris, Paul Novik, Harvey O'Connor, Louise Patterson, George Rawick, Lester Rodney, Annette Rubinstein, Pete Seeger, Norman Thomas, Stan Weir, Myra Tanner Weiss.
Several group interviews or conferences were recorded pertaining to the following organizations: Catholic Worker Movement, International Labor Defense, Johnson-Forest Tendency, Matteotti Club, Medem Jewish Socialist Group, Socialist Party(U.S.), Southern Negro Youth Congress, Workers Party (1940-1949), Workers Party (1940-1949).
Arrangement
Alphabetical by name.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Container list
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born..; Baxandall, Rosalyn Fraad, 1939- --Interviews.; Berrigan, Daniel--Interviews.; Berry, Abner--Interviews.; Bloom, Jonathan.; Boggs, James--Interviews.; Breitman, George--Interviews.; Buhle, Paul, 1944-; Chernin, Rose--Interviews.; Communist Party of the United States of America--Interviews..; Cowley, Malcolm, 1898- --Interviews.; Darcy, Samuel, 1905- --Interviews.; De Leon, Solon, 1883-1975--Interviews.; Draper, Hal--Interviews.; Dunayevskaya, Raya--Interviews.; Epstein, Melech--Interviews.; Ferlinghetti, Lawrence--Interviews.; Foner, Henry--Interviews.; Foner, Moe, 1915- --Interviews.; Gellert, Hugo, 1892-1985--Interviews.; Gitlin, Todd--Interviews.; Glaberman, Martin--Interviews.; Glotzer, Albert, 1908-1999--Interviews.; Goldberg, Itshe--Interviews.; Harap, Louis--Interviews.; Harrington, Michael, 1928- --Interviews.; Industrial Workers of the World--Interviews.; International Labor Defense--Interviews.; James, C. L. R. (Cyril Lionel Robert), 1901- --Interviews.; Johnson, Howard, 1915- --Interviews.; Johnson-Forest Tendency--Interviews.; Kolehmainen, Mary--Interviews.; Le Sueur, Meridel--Interviews.; Lemisch, Bea.; Magil, A. B. --Interviews.; Matteotti Club--Interviews.; McGrath, Thomas--Interviews.; McKinney, Ernest Rice, 1886-1984--Interviews.; McLevy, Jasper--Interviews.; Nelson, Steve, 1903- --Interviews.; Novick, P., 1891- --Interviews.; O'Connor, Harvey, 1897-1987--Interviews.; Patterson, Louise Thompson, 1901-1999--Interviews.; Prago, Ruth.; Rawick, George P., 1929- --Interviews.; Rodney, Lester, 1911- --Interviews.; Rubinstein, Annette T. (Annette Teta), 1910-2007--Interviews.; Seeger, Pete, 1919- --Interviews.; Socialist Party (U.S.)--Interviews.; Socialist Workers Party--Interviews.; Southern Negro Youth Congress--Interviews.; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.)--Interviews.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968--Interviews.; Trade Union Unity League (U.S.).; Weir, Stan--Interviews.; Weiss, Myra Tanner--Interviews.; Workers Party (1940-1949)--Interviews.; Workmen's Circle/Arbeiter Ring--Interviews.; Young Communist League of the U.S.; African American radicals--Interviews.; Anarchism--United States.; Anarchists--United States--Interviews.; Communism--United States.; Communists--United States--Interviews.; Emigration and immigration--United States--Interviews.; Finnish American radicals--Interviews.; Hungarian American radicals--Interviews.; Italian American radicals--Interviews.; Jewish radicals--United States--Interviews.; Labor union members--United States--Interviews.; Labor unions--United States.; Labor--United States.; Oral histories (document genre); Right and left (Political science); Slavic American radicals--Interviews.; Socialism--Bridgeport (Conn.); Socialism--United States.; Socialists--United States--Interviews.; Spain--History--Civil War, 1936-1939--Participation, American--Interviews.; Student movements--United States--Interviews.; Trotskyists--United States--Interviews.; Women employees--United States--Interviews.; Women radicals--United States--Interviews.
- A
  - Name: Alesh, Minka Description: SNPJ (Slovenian Benefit Society), 1910- present; Haberdashery Union, New York and Chicago, c. 1910-20; Women's activities in Chicago; SNPJ and Socialist Party, 1910s- 1920s., Oct 26, 1982 (Box 1)
    General note
    Index available
    tape#: 1 U2A
  - Name: Alvarez, Jose Description: Origins of Spanish language Communist movement in Ybor City, Florida, 1920s- 1930s; community support of Communists and relation to surrounding communities, 1930s-40s; immigration from Spain, work in tobacco factories and activities of unions, 1920s-40s; Red Scare decimation of Ybor City Left, 1950s; meeting with Fidel Castro before Cuban Revolution, 1950s., Mar 15, 1983 (Box 1)
    Transcript and index available
    tape#: 2 U2A
  - Name: Amter, Vicky Description: Communist Party, lower east side, N.Y., 1940s-1960s; conflicts with her father, a Socialist; experiences as Local 65 shop steward; Jefferson School; harassment and isolation of CP in the 1950s; reactions to emergence of the New Left., Feb 19, 1978 (Box 1)
    no tape
  - Name: Aptheker, Herbert Description: College radicalism in 1930s; MA thesis on Nat Turner; joining the Communist Party; status in academic life; Jefferson School., 1976 (Box 1)
    Transcript available
  - Name: Aronek, Harry Description: Immigration; political and cultural activities in New York Jewish community, 1930s-1950s., Oct 25, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Name: Aspitz, Jacob Description: Los Angeles Jewish Left since 1930s; rise of anti-Nazi "front" across Jewish community and Communists' participation in it; isola- tion of Jewish Left during Cold War; literary interests and old age around Yiddishe Kultur Farband., Apr 8, 1970 (Box 1)
- B
  - Name: Banach, Stanley Description: Neighborhood background in Providence, 1950s; Army life in Vietnam and in Germany, radical influences; union activity at Electric Boat/Quonset Point, Rhode Island, organizing drive; union activity at Brown and Sharpe before and during 1982 strike; political philosophy and aspirations., Apr 11, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Name: Barnett, Eugene Description: Industrial Workers of the World, Northwest U.S., 1910s; West Virginia coal miners at turn of century; becoming a unionist; lumber work in Northwest; repression in Centralia., Early 1940s (Box 1)
  - Name: Barry, Walter Description: Boyhood and first labor experience in Endicott, N.Y.; Trade Union Unity League and United Electrical Workers District 4, Westinghouse Elevator plant, Jersey City, N.J., 1930s-50s., Oct 12, 1980-Feb 4, 1980 (Box 1)
    tape#: 3 U2A
  - Name: Baxandall, Rosalyn Description: Background in New York Old Left; cultural awakening in Madison; political and cultural experiences in Madison, 1958-60s; beginnings of Madison's women's movement., Nov 8, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Name: Bazell, Bertha Description: Born 1896; immigrant Jewish background; Workman's Circle; Communist Party, 1930s-50s in Coney Island, N.Y.; later Fall River, Mass.; harassment by the F.B.I. in the 1950s., Mar 10, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Name: Bell, Ray Description: Socialism/communism, Spain in WWII NOT IN OHAL GUIDE, Aug 2, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Name: Bennett, Fay Description: College anti-war movement, 1930s; American Student Union; Keep America Out of War Congress, late 1930s; experience of con- scientious objectors during World War II; postwar work with National Sharecroppers' Fund., May 26, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Name: Bergen, Jack Description: Bridgeport in 1910s; Depression and Jasper McLevy; SP in Connecticut state politics, 1930s., 1967 (Box 1)
  - Name: Bernard, John T. Description: Mesaba Park Coop. Assn. tribute to John (Tribute to) Bernard, U.S. representative 1936-38; speeches by former Minnesota Governor Elmer Benson and others about Bernard's record in Congress; response from Bernard; music., Jun 25, 1977 (Box 1)
    tape#: 3 U2B
  - Name: Berrigan, Daniel Description: Last interview before he went underground and then to prison; reflections on his activities during the 1960s including Catonsville incident., Apr 1, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Name: Berry, Abner Description: Communist Party in Harlem, 1930s; Ethiopia Defense Committee; Unemployed Councils; Richard Wright and CP cultural policies; CP branches and organizers in Harlem; opposition to CP in Harlem., 1974-1977 (Box 1)
    tape#: 6 U2B
  - Name: Beumer, Steve Description: Family background in Indiana and political activities there and in Detroit, late 1960s- 1970s; Socialist Workers Party; experiences as bus driver and union activist in Detroit., Jun 21, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Name: Birnbaum, Martin Description: Life and activities of Yiddish "proletarian poet"; childhood, immigration and literary work for New Yorker Volkszeitung, 1920s; friendship with Moshe Nadir; role of Left in Yiddish literary community, the group Proletpen; disillusionment with Communism and poetic realism, return to unrestrained lyricism., 1978 (Box 1)
  - Name: Birnbaum, Martin Description: The meaning of the "sense of humor" in Yiddish literary work; Birnbaum's own sense of humor contrasted to that of Moshe Nadir and to that of Jewish popular culture., 1983 (Box 1)
  - Name: Blair, Fred Description: Role of ethnicity in Communist Party of Wisconsin, 1930s-40s; support of Left from Polish sector dating back to 1880, support of other Slav groups from 1910s; role of Meta Berger in Wisconsin Party and Blair's ascendency to state leadership; unemployment demonstration in Milwaukee and influence on students in Madison, University of Wis- consin; increase of District membership with addition of northern Wisconsin; character of northern Wisconsin rural Communists; exodus of rural Communists from state, 1940s-50s; McCarthyism and decline of Communist support., Jul 26, 1983 (Box 1)
    tape#: 1 U2C
  - Name: Bloomfield, Norman Description: Young People's Socialist League, 1930s; split in Trotskyism; Berkeley campus; work in shipyards., May 7, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Name: Boggs, Grace Lee Description: Asian-American family background in Providence, R.I.; education and involvement in radical politics in New York, late 1930s; Workers Party and Johnson-Forest tendency, 1940s; Correspondence (Detroit, 1950s); involvement in the black movement with her husband, James Boggs; comments on C.L.R. James., Mar 28, 1983 (Box 1)
    tape#: 2 U2C
  - Name: Boggs, James Description: Youth in the South; factory life in Detroit, 1930s-40s; Johnson-Forest Tendency; activi- ties in 1960s-70s., Mar 29, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Name: Booth, Paul Description: Students for a Democratic Society, 1960s, Oct 1969 (Box 1)
  - Name: Borun, Fannie Description: Political struggles within the International Ladies Garment Workers Union, 1920s; experiences on trips in the Soviet Union, 1930s; women and the Communist Party, Jan 6, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Name: Boudon, Judy Description: Immigration from Panama; Spanish immigrant community in New York, 1930s; office and factory work; America Labor Party; Communist Party, and women in the CP., Feb 8, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Name: Brandon, Thomas Description: Workers' Newsreel and Film and Photo League, early 1930s., Nov 4, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Name: Brecher, Jeremy Description: Students for a Democratic Society, 1962-65, Mar 31, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Name: Breitman, George Description: Unemployed organizations in New Jersey, 1930s; Socialist Workers Party, 1938-54 in New Jersey., Jan 4, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Name: Brier, Harry Description: East End of London, 1920s-30s; Jewish character of Communist support; anti- fascist activities in London, 1920-30s; immigration to Los Angeles and union activities, 1940s-present., Aug 26, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Name: Brise, Theodore Description: Anarchism and Arbeter Ring, Los Angeles; Yiddish anarchist activists and the Rudolf Rocker Circle., Apr 18, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Name: Brookwood Labor College Description: Narration by Jon Bloom of slide show on history of Brookwood Labor College and Workers' Education Local 189, with comments by former Brookwood staff and students., Oct 10, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Name: Brorsen, Niki Description: Family background and growing up in San Francisco and Chicago, 1950s-60s; anti-war work and decision to join Young Socialist Alliance, late 1960s; work as a waitress and activities in restaurant union, 1970s., Oct 10, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Name: Buch, Peter Description: Immigration from Turkey and youth in Los Angeles; brief involvement in Socialist Zionism, early 1950s; Socialist Workers Party and Young Socialist Alliance, Los Angeles and nationally, 1950s-60s, including involvement in Robert Williams case, responses to Cuban Revolution and Vietnam War., Aug 24, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Name: Burbank, David Description: Saint Louis radicalism, 1930s; Socialist Party, American Workers Party, Trotskyist movement, Workers Party; CLR James in Missouri; gas workers' unionization., Oct 6, 1984 (Box 1)
    tape#: 1 U2D
  - Name: Burlak, Ann Description: Rhode Island Labor activities, early 1930s, and her own role as a Communist speaker, activist, organizer in Providence and Pawtucket., 1977 (Box 1)
    tape#: 6 U2D
- C
  - Name: Cantor, Fanny & Herman Description: Immigration to US from Russia and development of social consciousness; growing up in New York's Hell's Kitchen; radicalism and cooperativism, 1920s-30s; reflections on current issues and younger radicals., Jan 11, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Name: Caplowitz, Philip Description: Immigration; activities of Jewish Communists in unions, 1920s-30s; Yiddish Culture and Yiddishe Kultur Farband, 1930s-present., Nov 15, 1980 (Box 1)
    tape#: 2 U2D
  - Name: Carroll, Wendell Description: American Youth for Democracy, late 1940s; Independent Socialist League, early 1950s; ISL positions on Korean War, Rosenberg case, Communist Party and McCarthyism, race and civil rights., Nov 30, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Name: Caruso, Pincus Description: Origins of Labor (Poale) Zionism in Eastern Europe and Caruso's role, early years of century; formation and publication of Yiddishe Kempfer, New York; growth of Poale Zionism in World War I era and brief publication of daily Zionist newspaper; growth of Zionism in 1930s-40s and support of Israel; reflections on failure of Zionists as regards Arab inhabitants, 1930s onward, and about conservative Israeli leadership., Mar 16, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Name: Catholic Worker Conference Description: Program to honor Dorothy Day and founding of the Catholic Worker; panel comments by John Cort and others on Dorothy Day's character and the influence of the Worker. Trinity College, Worcester, Massachusetts., May 2, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Name: Chasanow, Bernard Description: Narrative translation of part of his 1956 Yiddish autobiography, Days and Years., 1978 (Box 1)
    tape#: 3 U2D
  - Name: Chasanow, Bernard Description: ILGWU, 1909-1928; Political activist in Russia, 1898-1909., May 31, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Name: Chase, Rev. Don Description: Activities against US intervention in Nicaragua, 1928; Christian Socialism in San Francisco parish, 1930s-50s; interpretation of Liberation Theology, 1970s-80s., Nov 5, 1983 (Box 1)
    tape#: 2 U2E
  - Name: Chernin, Rose Description: Origins and activities of Los Angeles branch, Committee for the Protection of the Foreign Born, 1940s-1950s; family life, problems and differences with daughter., Oct 25, 1983 (Box 1)
    tape#: 1 U2E
  - Name: Christoffel, Harold Description: Early union background, 1930s, of former president of United Auto Workers Local 248 (Allis Chalmers), Milwaukee, Wisconsin., Jun 27, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Name: Ciminelli, Helen Description: Activities of SNPJ (Slovenian Benefit Society) in Fontana, California, 1930s- present; SNPJ role in Henry Wallace campaign., Oct 6, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Name: Citron, Alice Description: Harlem teacher, 1930s-1940s; Teachers's Union; her dismissal during McCarthy era and struggle for reinstatement., Jan 6, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Name: CCNY Memorial Description: Recording of Dedication of memorial for 13 CCNY alumni members of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade killed in action in the Spanish Civil War., Apr 13, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Name: Clemente, Edigio Description: Editor of La Parole, and secretary of Italian Socialist Federation, 1390s., May 11, 1981 (Box 1)
    tape#: 1 2UE
  - Name: Cloud, Lucy Ann Description: Industrial Workers of the World Centralia, Wash. case, 1919, with particular reference to Elmer Smith, IWW attorney., Aug 25, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Name: Cohen, Rose Description: Recollections of studies at the Jefferson School of Social Science., Apr 12, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Name: Cohen, Joseph & Ruth Description: On "Carlo" (Jesse Cohen), the cartoonist of the Workers Party, 1940s., Jun 9, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Name: Corey, Olga Description: Experiences of Louis Fraina/Lewis Corey's daughter; reaction to the movie Reds; reminiscences of father at Antioch College, 1940s; her own union activities., Jan 18, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Name: Cortez, Carlos Description: Son of Mexican-American activist who joined Industrial Workers of the World after San Diego Free Speech Fight; father's life in Milwaukee, 1920s; mother, German-American Socialist and poet; Cortez' imprisonment during World War II as conscientious objector; role of IWW in Chicago Mexican- American community, 1940s; Cortez' role as artist and speaker for IWW, 1940s-present; anarchism and IWW., Jul 25, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Name: Cowley, Malcolm Description: Left in the Depression; League of Professional Groups, "Culture and the Crisis," 1932; the proletarian novel; John Reed Clubs; Popular Front; Spanish Civil War; reflections., Jan 19, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Name: Cvetas, Joseph Description: Family background in SNPJ (Slovenian Benefit Society); fraternal activities as child; fraternalism today., Oct 23, 1982 (Box 1)
- D
  - Name: Darcy, Sam Description: Immigrant background; Communist activities, 1920s; factionalism; Browderism; leaves CP; subsequent activities and reflections. [See also Sam Darcy Papers, Tamiment Library]., 1981 (Box 1)
    tape#: 2 U2F
  - Name: Davidson, Saul Description: "United Front" of various organizations for preservation of Yiddish language in Miami Beach; Davidson as former left activist become mainstream Yiddish activist; reflections on survival of Yiddish., Mar 16, 1983 (Box 1)
    tape#: 1 U2F
  - Name: Davis, Sam Description: Role of Jewish Left in New Haven, Conn. since 1920s; nature of Jewish community; split of Socialists and Communists, 1920s; Yiddishe Kultur Farband choir and other activities; separation of Morgen Freiheit supporters from Communists and cultural activities in YKUF/Jewish Currents circle., Nov 15, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Name: Deak, Zoltan Description: Aesthetics of Hungarian-American radical press, Uj Elore and Hungarian Word, 1920s- present; immigration and interest in progressive press; circulation and internal structure of Uj Elore; shrinking of Hungarian-American milieu., Feb 17, 1983 (Box 1)